A Register of the Albert J. and Roberta Wohlstetter Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Albert J. and Roberta Wohlstetter Papers
1929-2007
97076
Wohlstetter, Albert J.
Wohlstetter, Roberta.
844 manuscript boxes, 5 card file boxes, 8 oversize boxes 342.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Contains speeches and writings, correspondence, notes, memoranda, reports, studies, and printed matter; relating to American military and national security policy, nuclear warfare strategic planning, and nuclear proliferation issues. Includes the papers of Roberta Wohlstetter, wife of Albert J. Wohlstetter.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research except for: Boxes 1-61, 201-354, 385-754, 815-821 and 838-857 which are closed
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1997
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Albert J. Wohlstetter Biographical Note
1913 December 19 Born in New York City
1934 B.A., College of the City of New York
1934-1935 Studied, Columbia University Law School
1937 M.A. in mathematical and symbolic logic from Columbia University, Graduate School of Philosophy
1939 Married Roberta Morgan
1941-1942 Research Associate, National Bureau of Economic Research
1942-1943 Consultant, Planning Committee, War Production Board
1942-1945 Factory Manager and Quality Control Manager, Atlas Aircraft Products Corporation
1945-1946 Director of Research, General Panel Corporation, New York
1946-1947 Program director, National Housing Agency, Washington, D.C.
1947-1951 Vice President, then President, General Panel Corporation, Burbank, California
1951-1997 Senior Analyst and Consultant, Rand Corporation, Economics Department
1958 Adviser to United States delegation, Geneva Conference on Surprise Attack
1961-1967 Consultant to the Assistant Secretary of Defense, and thereafter consultant to the Department of Defense throughout his career
1962 Adviser to President John F. Kennedy during the Cuban Missile Crisis
1962-1964 Ford Professor, Universities of California at Berkeley, and visiting professor at Los Angeles
1964-1972 Served as consultant to various corporations and institutions, including Research & Analysis Corp., Stanford Research Institute, General Electric, and the Northrop Corporation
1964-1980 University Professor, later University Professor Emeritus, University of Chicago
1965 Author (with Roberta Wohlstetter), Controlling the Risks in Cuba
1965, 1976 Awarded Medal for Distinguished Service, Department of Defense
1969-1971 Consultant to the National Security Council, Washington D.C.
1970-1971 Fellow, All Souls College, Oxford, England
1970-1992 Member, Executive Committee and Director, Strategy Group, California Seminar on Arms Control and Foreign Policy (also known as California Seminar on International Security and Foreign Policy)
1971?-1997 Member, Chief of Naval Operations Executive Panel
1974-1997 Founding partner and Senior Consultant, PanHeuristics, affiliated with Science Applications Inc., and subsequently with RDA
1975-? President, European American Institute for Security Research (EAI)
1975-1988? Chairman, New Alternatives Workshop
1979 Author (with Roberta Wohlstetter), Swords from Plowshares: The Military Potential of Civilian Nuclear Energy
1979-1992? Vice President, Security Conference on Asia and Pacific (SECAP)
198?-1997 President, American Institute for Strategic Cooperation (AISC)
1980-1997 Senior Research Fellow, Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace, Stanford University
1985 Author, Between an Unfree World and None: Increasing Our Choices
1985 November Albert and Roberta Wohlstetter jointly awarded Medal of Freedom by President Reagan
1985-1992 Member, President's Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board (PFIAB)
1986-1992 Member, Defense Policy Board
1986 Appointed Co-Chairman of the Presidential Commission of Integrated Long-Term Strategy
1990-1997 Active in the affairs of the Balkan Institute
1994 Honorary Ph.D., City University of New York
1997 January 10 Died, Los Angeles, California
Roberta Wohlstetter Biographical Note
1912 August 22 Born, Duluth, Minnesota
1930 Summer Studied, Stanford University
1931 Summer Studied, Sorbonne, Paris
1932 Summer Studied, University of Heidelberg
1933 B.A., Vassar College
1934-1935 Studied, Columbia University Law School
1936 M.A. in psychology, Columbia University
1937 M.A. in comparative literature, Radcliffe College
1937-1938 Teaching assistant, University of Southern California
1939 Married Albert Wohlstetter
Early 1940s Taught at Barnard College
Mid 1940s Taught at Howard University Attended Washington School of Psychiatry
1947-2002 Consultant, Rand Corporation, Social Science Department
1962 Author, Pearl Harbor: Warning and Decision
1962 Awarded the Bancroft Prize in Diplomatic History
1963 Named the Los Angeles Times Woman of the Year
1965 Author (with Albert Wohlstetter), Controlling the Risks in Cuba
1965-1968? Taught at the University of Chicago
1970-2007 Member, Council on Foreign Relations (first woman to be invited to join)
1970-1971 Fellow, St. Hilda's College, Oxford, England
1970-1992 Member, California Seminar on Arms Control and Foreign Policy (also known as California Seminar on International Security and Foreign Policy)
1979 Author (with Albert Wohlstetter), Swords from Plowshares: The Military Potential of Civilian Nuclear Energy
1979-1982 Member, Defense Science Board
1981-1985 Member, Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA) Advisory Board, Ad Hoc Task Force on Terrorism
1982-1984 Consultant, Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA)
1985 November Awarded (with Albert Wohlstetter) the Medal of Freedom by President Reagan
1986-1989 Consultant, Assistant Secretary of Defense for International Security Policy
1988-1998 Consultant to the Director, Net Assessment
1994-2007 Served on Board of Advisors, Nonproliferation Policy Education Center (NPEC)
1997 Awarded the Defense Special Weapons Agency Lifetime Achievement Medal
2007 January 6 Died, Manhattan, New York
Scope and Content of Collection
Contains speeches and writings, correspondence, notes, memoranda, reports, studies, and printed matter; relating to American military and national security policy, nuclear warfare strategic planning, and nuclear proliferation issues. Includes the papers of Roberta Wohlstetter, wife of Albert J. Wohlstetter.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into ten series: Speeches and Writings, Roberta Wohlstetter File, Printed Matter, Photographs, Microfilm, Videotapes, Maps, Memorabilia, Card File, and Oversize Materials.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in Stanford University's online catalog.
Subjects
Nuclear weapons.; Security, International.; United States--Defenses.; United States--Military policy.
Container List
- CLOSED (Box 1-61)
- Speeches and Writings, 1936-1996. (Box 62)
  This series includes background materials consisting of charts, graphs, maps, and transparencies used for presentation; briefings by and for Albert Wohlstetter; conferences he attended arranged in a general section and conferences he participated in arranged thereafter in chronological order; interviews by and of him; letters to the editor and newspaper articles; notes, a unique feature of his papers, arranged in chronological order, including short articles characterized by him as 'notes'; research materials, including related correspondence and memoranda, notes, and some drafts possibly used in his writings; speeches, including conversations, telephone and conference calls; statements and testimonies; and finally his writings, all arranged alphabetically by physical form and therein chronologically
  - Background materials
    - Charts.
      Includes related materials
      - General
        - General. (Folder 62: 1-4)
          Includes materials relating to Albert Wohlstetter's typescript comments on "Combat Radii of Soviet Fighter Escorts and Backfire Bomber," 1982 September 10
        - Briefing charts. (Folder 62: 5-6)
          Includes an article by Brian Chow, 1982 June 25
      - Former Yugoslavia – Population (Folder 62: 7)
      - Nuclear weapons. (Folder 62: 8-11)
        Includes industrial targets
      - Persian Gulf War, 1991 (Box-folder 63: 1-3)
        (Operation Desert Storm)
      - Plutonium (Folder 63: 4)
      - Soviet Union (Folder 63: 5)
      - United States - Armed forces - Appropriations and expenditures (Folder 63: 6)
      - United States. Army - Airborne troops (Folder 63: 7)
      - United States. Army - Equipment (Folder 63: 8)
      - United States versus Soviet Union. (Folder 63: 9-13)
        Includes areas of defense spending and investment, airlift capacity, etc.
      - United States versus Soviet Union. (Box-folder 64: 1-3)
      - Miscellany (Folder 64: 4)
    - Computer printouts (Folder 64: 5)
    - Graphs
      - General (Folder 64: 6)
      - United States (Folder 64: 7)
      - United States versus Soviet Union (Folder 64: 8-10)
    - Maps.
      - General (Folder 64: 11)
      - General (Box-folder 65: 1)
      - Afghanistan (Folder 65: 2)
      - Backfire range (Folder 65: 3)
      - Balkan States (Folder 65: 4)
      - Bosnia (Folder 65: 5-6)
      - China (Folder 65: 7)
      - Contingency areas (Folder 65: 8)
      - Developing countries (Folder 65: 9)
      - Greece – Expansion (Folder 65: 10)
      - Indian Ocean (Folder 65: 11)
      - Iran-Iraq (Box-folder 66: 1)
      - Japan (Folder 66: 2)
      - Kabul (Afghanistan) (Folder 66: 3)
      - Korea (South) (Folder 66: 4)
      - Kuwait (Folder 66: 5)
      - Middle East (Folder 66: 6)
      - North Atlantic Treaty Organization (combat coverage) (Folder 66: 7)
      - Pakistan (Folder 66: 8)
      - Persian Gulf Region (air access, 1950s-1979) (Folder 66: 9)
      - Persian Gulf War, 1991 (Folder 66: 10)
      - Saudi Arabia (Folder 66: 11)
      - Serbia – Expansion (Folder 66: 12)
      - Soviet Union (Folder 66: 13)
      - Soviet Union - Armed forces (combat coverage) (Folder 66: 14)
      - Soviet Union. Voenno-Morskoi flot (Soviet Union. Navy) (Folder 66: 15)
      - Turkey (Folder 66: 16)
      - United States (Folder 66: 17)
      - Miscellany (Folder 66: 18)
    - Transparencies., See also Oversize File
      Includes related materials.
      - General (Folder 66: 19)
      - Developing countries – Defenses (Folder 66: 20)
      - North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) (Folder 66: 21)
      - Soviet Union (Folder 66: 22)
      - Turkey (Folder 66: 23)
      - United Kingdom - Libya (Folder 66: 24)
      - United States versus Soviet Union (Folder 66: 25-26)
      - Miscellany (Folder 66: 27)
  - Briefings. (Box 67)
    Includes related materials. Typescript unless otherwise noted
    - By Albert Wohlstetter
      - Undated
        - Persian Gulf. (Folder 67: 1)
          Holograph
        - RAND Cuban study (with Roberta Wohlstetter). (Folder 67: 2)
      - Military Advisory Group, 1955 (Folder 67: 3)
      - AFDAP Committee (Kybal), 1955 September 27 (Folder 67: 4)
      - Major General Fred Smith, Ent Air Force Base, Colorado, 1955 December 5-6. (Folder 67: 5)
        Includes holograph
      - Ramo-Wooldridge Pilot Study of Advanced Ballistic Missiles, 1957 (Folder 67: 6)
      - Critique on ORO-R-17
        - Scientific Advisory Board, 1958 March 21 (Folder 67: 7)
        - Board of Trustees, 1958 March 27 (Folder 67: 8)
      - "Offense Study for General Cary,", 1958 April 4. (Folder 67: 9)
        Includes revised? version, 1958 July 14, and holograph
      - SOFS, 1959 September 17 (Folder 67: 10)
      - SRI-DEPEX, 1965 September 16 (Folder 67: 11)
      - "Everybody's Tocqueville: Differences Making for Revolt,", 1970? (Folder 67: 12)
      - AFAG, Tactical Studies Program, 1971 January 6 (Folder 67: 13)
      - Arms race, 1973 August 30 (Folder 67: 14)
      - Persian Gulf, 1979-1980. (Folder 67: 15-19)
      - "Broad Problems and Specific Means Programmed So Far,", 1985 December 6. (Box-folder 68: 1)
        Includes revised versions, 1986 February-July, and an outline for briefing on 1986 February 13
      - Sandia, Livermore Lab, 1989 December (Folder 68: 2)
    - For Albert Wohlstetter. Briefing by Alan Fogelquist, 1995 September 17. (Folder 68: 3)
  - Conferences, 1959-1996.; See also
    Includes presentations at seminars, symposia, and workshops, often attended by Roberta Wohlstetter as well. Also includes correspondence with Roberta Wohlstetter.
  - Roberta Wohlstetter File, 1933-1996.
    This series deals exclusively with her life and career and includes writings that she alone authored, while writings and studies co-authored with her husband are to be found in the other series. It consists of a biographical file including her achievements during her undergraduate and graduate years, awards received by her, a career file reflecting her association with the Rand Corporation and PanHeuristics, conferences she participated in, interviews, letters to the editor, notes, research materials used in her writings, speeches, her consulting work with various government agencies relating to defense issues, and finally her writings, arranged alphabetically by physical form
    - General
      - Undated (Folder 68: 4)
      - 1959-1964 (Folder 68: 5-10)
      - 1969 (Folder 68: 11-12)
      - 1969 (Box-folder 69: 1)
      - 1970 May-December (Folder 69: 2-5)
      - 1971 December – 1973 November (Folder 69: 6-10)
      - 1974 August – 1984 April (Box 70)
      - 1984 June – 1996 October (Box 71)
    - Remarks, ORO Conference, n.d. (Box 72)
      - Notes (Folder 72: 1)
      - Outline (Folder 72: 2)
    - Remarks, Strategy I Workshop, n.d. (Folder 72: 3)
      Notes
    - Remarks, Surprise Attack Conference, RAND, Santa Monica, California, 1959 January 29
      - General (Folder 72: 4)
      - Correspondence (Folder 72: 5)
      - Notes (Folder 72: 6)
    - "National Decisions Concerning Defense," paper, Second International Conference on Operational Research, Aix-en-Provence, France, 1960 September
      - Typescript (Folder 72: 7)
    - Printed copies, 1960 (proceedings of the conference), and 1964 (expanded version under the title "Analysis and Design of Conflict Systems," chapter 7 for a RAND publication) (Folder 72: 8)
    - "On NATO Talk," remarks, Tenth Bilderberg Conference, St-Castin, Canada, 1961 April 21-23
      - General (Folder 72: 9)
      - Background materials (Folder 72: 10)
      - Correspondence (Folder 72: 11)
      - Notes (Folder 72: 12)
      - Outline (Folder 72: 13)
    - Remarks, The Scientist as a Participant in Government, and The Scientific Community: Patterns for Participation in Government, Civil Science Relations Seminar, Council for Atomic Age Studies, Columbia University, New York, 1962 February 5
      - General (Folder 72: 14)
      - Correspondence. (Folder 72: 15)
        Includes remarks (partial)
    - "Scientists, Seers and Strategy," remarks., See also Speeches and Writings/ Writings (Folder 72: 16)
      Includes participation in discussion on the Scientific Strategists and Civil-Military Relations, and Scientists, Foreign Policy, and Politics, Civil-Science Relations Seminar, Council for Atomic Age Studies, Columbia University, New York, 1962 March 12. Typescript. Includes typewritten transcript of discussion.
    - Remarks, the Institute of Strategic Studies Fourth Annual Conference, the Rheinhotel Dreesen, Bad Godesberg, Germany, 1962 June 30–July 2, and Fifth Annual Conference, Caius College, Cambridge, England, 1963 September 21-23
      - General (Folder 72: 17)
      - Background materials (Box-folder 73: 1)
      - Notes (Folder 73: 2)
      - Typescript (Folder 73: 3)
    - Remarks, Scientists and the Making of Public Policy conference, Council for Atomic Age Studies, Columbia University, New York, 1962 October 4-5
      - General (Folder 73: 4)
      - Typewritten transcript of discussion (Folder 73: 5)
    - "Arms Restraint in Military Decisions," speech, International Arms Control Symposium, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1962 December 19. (Folder 73: 6)
      Typescript
    - Remarks, FDR-Wilson Democratic Club Symposium, New York City, New York, 1963 June 11
      - General (Folder 73: 7)
      - Background materials (Folder 73: 8)
      - Notes (Folder 73: 9)
    - Paper, Fifth Annual Conference, Caius College, Cambridge, England, 1963 September 21-23.; See Institute of Strategic Studies Fourth Annual Conference, 1962 June 30–July 2
    - Remarks, Pacifism, Martyrdom, and Appeasement: On Influencing an Intractable Adversary by Non-Violent Means, American Psychological Association symposium, 1964 September 7
      - General (Folder 73: 10)
      - Background materials (Folder 73: 11)
      - Notes (Folder 73: 12)
      - Outline (Folder 73: 13)
    - Remarks, conference on disarmament and arms control problems in Asia between Japanese and American scholars, Tokyo, Japan, 1966 April 7-9
      - General (Folder 73: 14)
      - Background materials (Folder 73: 15)
      - Correspondence (Folder 73: 16)
      - Notes (Folder 73: 17)
      - Typescript. (Folder 73: 18)
        Includes a report on disarmament by Albert and Roberta Wohlstetter
    - "Theories in the Design and Choice of International Security Policies," paper, Harris Conference on New Approaches to International Relations, University of Chicago, Illinois, 1966 June 1-4. (Folder 73: 19)
      Outline
    - "Distant Wars and Far Out Estimates" (with Richard B. Rainey, Jr.), paper, American Political Science Association meeting, New York, 1966 September 8, and the Strategic Studies Conference sponsored by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Dedham, Massachusetts, 1966 September 9-11 (Box 74)
      - General (Folder 74: 1)
      - Background materials (Folder 74: 2)
      - Typescript summary, and revised version, 1967 January (Folder 74: 3-5)
    - "Atoms For Equality?" paper, Consultations Thirty and Thirty-One, Council on Religion and International Affairs, Washington, D.C., 1967 January 26 (Box 75)
      - General (Folder 75: 1)
      - Typescript (Folder 75: 2-3)
    - Participation, Ballistic Missile Defense seminar?, 1967 Spring. (Folder 75: 4)
    - Participation, Problems of Security in Asia, Indian Council of World Affairs, Institute of Strategic Studies, New Delhi, India, 1967 March 21-April 2
      - General (Folder 75: 5)
      - Background materials (Folder 75: 6)
      - Notes (Folder 75: 7)
    - "Strength, Interest and New Technologies," opening address, The Implications of Military Technology in the 1970's, International Institute for Strategic Studies Ninth Annual Conference, Elsinore, Denmark, 1967 September-October 1
      - Notes (Folder 75: 8)
      - Typescript. (Folder 75: 9)
        Includes "Technology, Capabilities and Interest in the 1970's"
      - Printed copy. Adelphi Papers, 1968 March (Box-folder 76: 1)
    - "On Vietnam and Bureaucracy," paper, Lessons and Mislessons of Vietnam conference, Adlai Stevenson Institute of International Affairs, Chicago, 1968 July 17. (Folder 76: 2)
      Typescript. Includes typescript outline and remarks, Council on Religion and International Affairs, Wisconsin, 1968 November
    - Participation, The U.S. as a World Power: Abundance and Scarcity, Council on Religion and International Affairs, Wisconsin, 1968 November 7-10
      - General (Folder 76: 3)
      - Correspondence (Folder 76: 4)
      - Notes (Folder 76: 5)
    - "Bases and the Reversion of Political Control in Okinawa," address, Japan-U.S. Kyoto Conference, 1969 January
      - General (Folder 76: 6)
      - Background materials (Folder 76: 7)
      - Correspondence (Folder 76: 8)
      - Typescript (Folder 76: 9)
    - "Scholarly Standards and Complex Political Choice, Rough Notes in not Quite Random Order," paper, Rules of Scholarly Self-Government Conference, Academy of Arts and Sciences, Boston, Massachusetts, 1970 November 13-14. (Box-folder 77: 1)
    - "Deterrence Models and Reality," U.S. Security and the Strategic Arms Race, discussion paper, Working Group I, Southern California Arms Control and Foreign Policy Seminar, 1971
      - Correspondence (Folder 77: 2)
      - Typescript (Folder 77: 3)
    - "Racial Economic Equality and Other Good But Different Things" (with Sinclair Coleman), paper, Center for the Study of Welfare Policy, University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois, 1971 November. (Folder 77: 4)
    - "Racial Economic Equality and Other Good but Different Things" (with Sinclair Coleman), paper, American Economic Association meeting, New Orleans, 1971 December.; See also 1971 November (Folder 77: 5)
      Typescript. Includes revised version, 1972 Spring.
    - Comments on stability, Working Group I on U.S. Security and the Strategic Arms Race, discussion meeting on draft paper by Leo Sartori, Southern California Arms Control and Foreign Policy Seminar, 1972 February 3
      - General (Folder 77: 6)
      - Notes (Folder 77: 7)
      - Typescript (Folder 77: 8)
    - "Security Policies of Japan as a Non-Nuclear State," paper, Conference on Peace in East Asia, Kyoto, Japan, 1972 June
      - General (Folder 77: 9)
      - Correspondence (Folder 77: 10)
      - Typescript (Folder 77: 11)
    - Remarks, Bureaucratic Behavior and the Strategic Arms Competition, Working Group I on U.S. Security and the Strategic Arms Race, discussion, draft paper by Andrew Marshall, Southern California Arms Control and Foreign Policy Seminar, 1972 September 9. (Folder 77: 12)
    - Remarks, Can Nuclear Deterrence Last Out the Century? Working Group II on Nuclear Strategy for the Long Run: Alternatives to Deterrence? Discussion, draft paper by Fred Ikle, Southern California Arms Control and Foreign Policy Seminar, 1972 September 11. (Folder 77: 13)
    - Participation, workshop, San Diego, California, 1973. (Folder 77: 14)
    - Remarks, Implications of PGMs: An Outline of a Briefing and Summary Report on the ARPA/RAND Seminar, RAND, Santa Monica, California, 1973 January 24. (Folder 77: 15)
    - "Deterring vs. Fighting," address, Amsterdam, Netherlands, 1973 February 16
      - Notes (Folder 77: 16)
      - Outline (Folder 77: 17)
    - "Contributions, Limits and Failings of the Experts in Advising on Complex Public Choices," paper, conference on The Role of the Scientist in a Democracy: Reconciling Expert Advice and Public Choice, Wingspread Center Conference, sponsored by Center for Policy Study, University of Chicago in cooperation with the Johnson Foundation, Wingspread, Racine, Wisconsin, 1973 May 24-25
      - General (Folder 77: 18)
      - Correspondence (Box-folder 78: 1)
      - Notes (Folder 78: 2)
      - Typescript, and typewritten transcripts of conference tapes (Folder 78: 3)
    - "Is There a Strategic Arms Race?" paper, California Arms Control and Foreign Policy Seminar, Helsinki, Finland, 1973 June 19-21
      - General (Folder 78: 4)
      - Background materials (Folder 78: 5)
      - Correspondence (Folder 78: 6)
      - Notes (Folder 78: 7)
      - Typescript (Folder 78: 8)
      - Typescript revised version, 1974 April (Box-folder 79: 1)
      - Printed copy. Foreign Policy, 1974 Summer (Folder 79: 2)